# Joey Chiao-Yin Hsiao, PhD

jcyhsiao@umich.edu • +1 (734) 730-0963 • http://joeyhsiao.info Ann Arbor, MI 48109, USA • Last Update: October, 2021

## RESEARCH INTEREST

I am a User Experience & Human-Computer Interaction researcher specialized in mixed-methods and longitudinal field studies. I am passionate about understanding how technologies influence user trust and community development. My PhD research focused on transnational newcomers' use of local e-commerce platforms, and contributed design recommendations that can largely improve this population's trust and commitment to their local communities and also the platforms.

## **EDUCATION**

University of Michigan Ann Arbor, MI, USA Ph.D in Information 09/2015 - 08/2021

Advisor: Dr. Tawanna R. Dillahunt

National Taiwan University Taipei, Taiwan 09/2010 - 06/2013

M.S. in Computer Science Advisor: Dr. Jane Yung-Jen Hsu

Carnegie Mellon University (Silicon Valley Campus) Moffett Field, CA, USA

Visiting Student 07/2012 - 09/2012

Advisor: Dr. Ted Selker

Taipei, Taiwan National Taiwan University

**B.S.** in Computer Science 09/2006 - 06/2010

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCES

UX Research & Consumer Insights Team, Yahoo Sunnyvale, CA, USA Starting 11/2021

**UX** Researcher

Lead the UX research of Yahoo's new e-commerce service.

Academic Research Collaborator (Remote) 09/2020 - 01/2021 Extended the internship research project by finishing up the project and contributing the results as an

academic research article (research manager: Frank Bentley)

#### UX Research Intern (Remote)

06/2020 - 08/2020

Led a project on exploring email-inspired information needs by conducting a series of studies, which included a two-week diary study, semi-structured interviews, and multiple online surveys (research manager: Frank Bentley)

Social Innovations Group, School of Information, Univ. of Michigan

Ann Arbor, MI, USA

#### Graduate Student Research Assistant

09/2015 - 08/2021

Lead research projects of the Social Innovations Group (SIG), which are focused on designing technologies to help low-resourced populations seek employment and education (Advisor: Dr. Tawanna R. Dillahunt)

UX Team, Intel-NTU IoX Center

Taipei, Taiwan

## Research Assistant

07/2014 - 07/2015

Carried out research on user experience and natural user interface under smart environment as the only M.S. member in the team (Advisor: Dr. Bing-Yu Chen)

## Workshop Organizer

03/2015 - 05/2015

Organized the collaborative workshop on design thinking of Stanford d.school and National Taiwan University IoX Center

Collaborative & Social Computing Lab, Dept. CS, Natl. Tsing-Hua Univ.

Hsinchu, Taiwan

#### Visiting Research Assistant

07/2014 - 07/2015

Led a project on friendsourcing, aiming to understand how social capital works when a SNS user requests resources on her/his own social network (Advisor: Dr. Hao-Chuan Wang)

Intelligent Agents Lab, Dept. CSIE, Natl. Taiwan Univ.

Taipei, Taiwan

#### System Administrator

03/2011 - 07/2013

Managed devices and web services for 30+ lab members

## **PUBLICATIONS**

#### Peer-Reviewed Journal Articles

- [J2] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. and Bentley, F. (2021). Exploring Email-Prompted Information Needs. *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction*, Vol. 5, CSCW 2, Article 474 (Honorable Mention).
- [J1] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. and Dillahunt, T. R. (2018). Technology to Support Immigrant Access to Social Capital and Adaptation to a New Country. *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction*, Vol. 2, CSCW, Article 70 (acceptance rate: 25.6%).

## Peer-Reviewed Conference Proceeding Papers

- [C8] Cherubini, M., Lu, A. J., Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Zhao, M., Aggarwal, A., and Dillahunt, T. R. (2021). Elucidating Skills for Job Seekers: Insights and Critical Concerns from a Field Deployment in Switzerland. In *Proc. of the 2021 ACM Designing Interactive Systems conference (DIS '21)*.
- [C7] Dillahunt, T. R., Israni A., Lu, A. J., Cai, M., and Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2021). Examining the Use of Online Platforms for Employment: A Survey of US Job Seekers. In *Proc. of the 2021 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '21)* (acceptance rate: 26.3%).
- [C6] Dillahunt, T. R. and Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2021). SkillsIdentifier: A Tool to Promote Career Identity and Self-efficacy Among Underrepresented Job Seekers. In *Proc. of The Annual Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (HICSS '21)* (Presenter).
- [C5] Dillahunt, T. R. and Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2020). Positive Feedback and Self-reflection: Features to Support Self-efficacy among Underrepresented Job Seekers. To appear in *Proc. of The ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems 2020 (CHI '20)* (acceptance rate: 24.3%; Presenter).
- [C4] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Moser, C., Schoenebeck, S., and Dillahunt, T. R. (2018). The Role of Demographics, Trust, Computer Self-efficacy, and Ease of Use in the Sharing Economy. In *Proc. of the 1st ACM SIGCAS Conference on Computing and Sustainable Societies (COMPASS '18)*, Article 37 (Presenter).
- [C3] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., and Dillahunt, T. R. (2017). People-Nearby Applications: How Newcomers Move Their Relationships Offline and Develop Social and Cultural Capital. In *Proc. of the 2017 ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW '17)*, 26-40 (acceptance rate: 33%; Presenter).
- [C2] Rajan, R., Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Lahoti, D., and Selker, T. (2013). "Roger that!" The Value of Adding Social Feedback in Audio-mediated Communications. In *Proc. of IFIP TC.13 International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction 2013 (INTERACT '13)*, 471-488 (acceptance rate: 31%).
- [C1] Tsai, W.-C., Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Lee, H.-C., Huang, C.-H., Hu, J.-C., Liang, R.-H., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2013). Designing a Reminiscence Aid in Personal Soundscape. In *Proc. of International Association of Societies of Design Research 2013 (IASDR '13)*, 5150-5160.

## Posters, Workshop Papers, and Presentations

- [P9] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. and Dillahunt, T. R. (2021) More than Shared Ethnicity: Shared Identity's Role in Transnational Newcomers' Trust in Local Consumer-to-Consumer E-commerce. In *The ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems Extended Abstract 2021 (CHI EA '21)* (Presenter).
- [P8] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2019) Fostering Immigrants' Trust in Online Local Social Exchange. Presented at The 22nd ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW '19), Doctoral Consortium (Presenter).
- [P7] Haimson, O. L., Semaan, B., Dym, B., Hsiao, J. C.-Y, Herron, D., and Moncur, W. (2019) Life Transitions and Social Technologies: Research and Design for Times of Life Change. Workshop at *The 22nd ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW '19)*.
- [P6] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Dillahunt, T. R. (2017) Detecting Life Changes: Increasing Opportunities to Benefit from People-Nearby Applications. In Proc. of *The ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems Extended Abstract 2017 (CHI EA '17)*, 1700 1707 (Presenter).
- [P5] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Pan, M.-H., Wang, H.-C., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2015) Let's Solve It Together: Introducing Crowd Workers to Friendsourcing for Improving Creative Design. Presented at *The Taiwan Computer-Human Interaction Workshop 2015 (Tai-CHI '15)* (Presenter).

- [P4] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Pan, M.-H., Wang, H.-C., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2015). The Price of the Priceless: Understanding Estimated Costs of Work in Friendsourcing. In *The ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems Extended Abstract 2015 (CHI EA '15)*, 1893-1898 (Presenter).
- [P3] Tsai, W.-C., Lee, H.-C., Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Liang, R.-H., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2013). Framing Design of Reminiscence Aids with Transactive Memory Theory. In *The ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems Extended Abstract 2013 (CHI EA '13)*, 331-336.
- [P2] Tsai, W.-C., Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Lee, H.-C., Huang, C.-H., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2012). In Search of Lost Sounds: Designing a Reminiscence Aid in Everyday Soundscape. Presented at *The ACM conference on Designing Interactive Systems 2012 (DIS '12)*.
- [P1] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Jih, W.-R., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2012). Recognizing Continuous Social Engagement Level in Dyadic Conversation by Using Turn-taking and Speech Emotion Patterns. Presented at AAAI '12 Activity Context Representation Workshop (ACR '12) (Presenter).

## Unpublished Theses and Research Reports

- [U4] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2021). Online and Offline Adaptation among Transnational Newcomers: Technology-mediated Social Exchange and Trust Development. *Dissertation*, School of Information, Univ. of Michigan.
- [U3] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2018). Social Network Matters: Opportunities for Technologies to Support Immigrants' Jobseeking. Field Prelim, School of Information, Univ. of Michigan.
- [U2] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2017). Can People-Nearby Applications Benefit Newly-Arrived Immigrants? An Exploratory Study. *Pre-candidacy research paper*, School of Information, Univ. of Michigan.
- [U1] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2012). Assessing Engagement in Conversation by Hierarchically Decomposing Emotion and Interaction. *Master's Thesis*, Dept. of Computer Science and Information Engineering (CSIE), Natl. Taiwan Univ.

## RESEARCH PROJECTS

Exploring Information Needs Sparked by Email

Research Leader Summer 2020

Exploring email-inspired information needs by conducting a series of mixed-method field studies, which included a two-week diary study with 50 participants, and three online surveys with 500+ respondents.

Designing Next-Generational Employment Tools for Underserved Job Seekers

Research Leader Fall 2018 - Summer 2021

Designing, deploying, and investigating novel employment tools' influences on resource-constrained job seekers' job search.

Designing Social Technologies to Support Newly Arrived Immigrants' Adaptation

Research Leader Summer 2016 - Summer 2021

Exploring socio-technical factors that affect recent immigrants' engagement in using social applications to interact with ethnically mixed user communities, and designing technology interventions that address these factors.

Investigating Factors Influencing Participation in the Sharing Economy

Research Assistant

Fall 2017 - Spring 2018

Examining the effects of online trust, demographics, and digital literacy on people's participating in the digital sharing economy.

Discovering People-Nearby Applications' Potential Benefits for People who Face Life Transitions

Research Leader

Fall 2015 - Spring 2016

Studying how people who are new to an area use people-nearby applications' (PNAs) to develop social capital and what are the concerns associated to their use.

## **HONORS**

University of Michigan

Ann Arbor, MI, USA

## Rackham Candidate Research Grant

2021

Was granted \$3,000 for conducting research on the project that explores immigrants' social technology use for adaptation.

Graham Sustainability Institute, University of Michigan

Ann Arbor, MI, USA

### Dow Sustainability Doctoral Fellowship

2020

Was granted \$15,000 for research on designing social technologies to support immigrants' adaptation and local communities' sustainability; Only ten UM doctoral candidates were granted with the fellowship.

University of Michigan

Ann Arbor, MI, USA

## Rackham Pre-candidate Research Grant

2016

Was granted \$1,500 for conducting research on the project that explores immigrants' social technology use for adaptation.

## PROFESSIONAL SERVICES

## Professional Events & Activities

ACM MobileHCI 2019 09/2017 - 10/2019

Student Volunteer Chair

Taiwan CHI 2015 01/2015 - 07/2015

Organizing Committee

OpenHCI Workshop 2014 (student-organized workshop on HCI in Taiwan) 01/2014 - 07/2014

Steering Committee

OpenHCI Workshop 2013 01/2013 - 07/2013

Program Chair

OpenHCI Workshop 2011 01/2011 - 07/2011

Registration and Volunteer Chair

#### Social Events & Activities

Univ. of Michigan, School of Information 08/2018 - 07/2019

Doctoral Committee - Student Representative

First Taiwan Night at CSCW 2019

Organizing Committee

Annual Taiwan Night at CHI 2015 - 2018

Organizing Committee

### **Mandatory Military Service**

Taiwan

## Company Chief Consultant (Second Lieutenant)

2013 - 2014

Handled psychological consulting, human resources management, and welfare of a military company with 40+ members

#### Peer Reviewer

ACM CHI 2017 - 2021; ACM CSCW 2017 - 2022; ACM DIS 2021; ACM Mobile<br/>HCI 2018 & 2019; ACM TEI 2017

# Conference Student Volunteer

ACM CSCW 2018, 2019; ACM COMPASS 2018; ACM CHI 2017

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### Teaching Assistant/Graduate Student Instructor

School of Information, Univ. of Michigan Winter 2018

SI-622: Usability Testing Instructor: Prof. Joyojeet Pal

School of Information, Univ. of Michigan Fall 2017

SI-501: Contextual Inquiry Instructor: Prof. Kentaro Toyama

Dept. CSIE, Natl. Taiwan Univ. &

Dept. Design, Natl. Taiwan Univ. of Tech. and Sci. Spring 2013

Advanced Human-Computer Interface/User-Oriented Innovation Design

Instructor: Prof. Hsien-Hui Tang & Prof. Mike Y. Chen

Dept. CSIE, Natl. Taiwan Univ. Fall 2011

Introduction to Computer Science Instructor: Prof. Jane Yung-Jen Hsu

Student Coach

OpenHCI Workshop 2011

07/2011

# SPEAKING ENGAGEMENT

Invited Panelist Taiwanese Association of Comp.-Hum. Interaction

TAICHI x CSCW Online Interview Room 08/2021

Invited Speaker School of Information, Univ. of Michigan

SI699: Mastery User Experience Research and Design 12/2019

Lightning Speaker Univ. of Michigan

iDEI: Talks at the Intersection of Information, Diversity, Equity & Inclusion 10/2018